<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="free_ipa">
  <title>Free IPA</title>

  <section>
    <title>Free IPA</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>
        This chapter describes the steps required to configure the
        authenticator which are specific to Windows, these instructions
        are prepared using Fedora 9 with Free IPA version 1.1.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pre-Requisits</title>

      <para>
        These instructions assume that you already have FreeIPA
        installed and correctly configured along with client already
        able to obtain Kerberos tickets.
      </para>

      <para>
        For documentation on how to install and configure FreeIPA please
        see
        <ulink url="http://www.freeipa.org/">
          http://www.freeipa.org/
        </ulink>
        .
      </para>

      <para>
        Also due to the supported encryption types of FreeIPA the JBoss
        application server is required to be running on a Java 6 JVM
        with unlimited cryptography enabled.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service Principal Creation</title>

      <para>
        In this example the test server is going to be accessible using
        the 'test_server.jboss.org' domain, the first step is to create
        the service principal which will represent this host.
      </para>

      <para>
        Full information on service principal creation is available
        within the FreeIPA documentation
        <ulink
          url="http://freeipa.org/page/AdministratorsGuide#Managing_Service_Principals">
          http://freeipa.org/page/AdministratorsGuide#Managing_Service_Principals
        </ulink>
      </para>

      <para>
        The easiest way to create a service principal is to make use of
        the FreeIPA WebUI when connected as an administrator and use the
        'Add Service Principal' link.
      </para>

      <figure id="ipa-add-service-principal">
        <title>Add Service Principal</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="images/ipa-add-service-principal.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        Set the hostname to the hostname of your server, in this case it
        is 'test_server.jboss.org', set the service type to HTTP and
        select 'Add Principal'.
      </para>

      <figure id="ipa-view-service-principal">
        <title>View Service Principal</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="images/ipa-view-service-principal.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <para>
          Creating the service principal requires the host name to be
          mapped using DNS, if this check fails you can instead create
          the principal using the following command from the command
          line
          <code>
            ipa-addservice HTTP/test_server.jboss.org@JBOSS.ORG --force
          </code>
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Export Keytab</title>

      <caution>
        <para>
          The steps to obtain the keytab reset the secret associated
          with the principal rendering all previosuly created keytabs
          for the principal invalid.
        </para>
      </caution>

      <para>
        Before exporting the keytab you will need to have used the kinit
        tool to obtain a Kerberos ticket-granting ticket for an
        administrator e.g.
        <code>kinit admin</code>
      </para>

      <para>
        The command to obtain the keytab is
        <code>ipa-getkeytab</code>
        with the following options: -
      </para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>-s The IPA server to obtain the keytab from.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>-p The principal to export.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>-k The name of the file to dump the keytab to.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <figure id="ipa-getkeytab">
        <title>Get Keytab</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="images/ipa-getkeytab.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        From this point on the server should be configured as described
        in
        <xref linkend="general_installation" />
        and tested using the Negotiation Toolkit as described in
        <xref linkend="negotiation_toolkit" />
        .
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>