<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction to JBoss Negotiation</title>

  <para>The JBoss Negotiation project provides a set of components to bring
  '<emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis>imple and <emphasis
  role="bold">P</emphasis>rotected GSSAPI <emphasis
  role="bold">Nego</emphasis>tiation Mechanism' or SPNEGO to JBoss.</para>

  <para>SPNEGO authentication allows a user already authenticated to a
  <emphasis role="bold">K</emphasis>erberos <emphasis
  role="bold">D</emphasis>omain <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>ontroller /
  KDC to silently authenticate to remote services without being prompted for
  further usernames and passwords. In addition to this the users credentials
  can be delegate to the remote system allowing the remote system to contact
  further systems as the user.</para>

  <para>Many web browsers provide support for SPNEGO authentication, this
  document focuses on <trademark>Microsoft Internet Explorer</trademark> and
  Mozilla Firefox. There are also a number of kerberos domain controllers
  available, this documentation focusses on <trademark>Microsoft Active
  Directory</trademark> and the MIT KDC implementation. Contributions for
  documentation on other web browsers and KDCs would be welcome.</para>

  <para></para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Components</title>

    <para>The JBoss Negotiation project provides the following components:
    -</para>

    <para></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>SPNEGO Authenticator and Login Module</para>

        <para>The authentication process is handled by a Tomcat Authenticator
        that and a JAAS login module, this combination achieves the
        integration with JBoss security.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Negotiation Toolkit</para>

        <para>This is a couple of utilities and a web application that can be
        used to test various aspects of your negotiation configuration to
        enable you to verify that the required steps are working correctly and
        to debug where failures may be occuring.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>General Authentication Process</title>

    <para>When working with the JBoss login modules and the existing
    authentication mechanisms work by asking the user to authenticate
    themseves by the client sending thier credentials to the server and then
    the login module verifying the credentials against either a local store of
    credentials or against a store on a remote repository such as a database
    server or a LDAP server.</para>

    <para>The SPNEGO authentication mechansim is slightly different.</para>

    <para></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Server Authentication</emphasis> - First
        the application server itself authenticates against the KDC and
        obtains it's own ticket.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Client Authentication</emphasis> - After
        the server prompt the client to authenticate the client responds with
        a SPNEGO token, the server then makes use of it's own ticket to decode
        the clients ticked and respond to the client.</para>

        <para>This process can take a couple of round trips for the client to
        authenticate against the server.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Mututal Authentication</emphasis> - If
        this is required it is even possible for the client to request that
        the server authenticates itself against the client.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Credential Delegation</emphasis> - A
        client can also be configured so that the credentials used for
        authentication can be delegated to the server, this means that the
        application server can then go on and call other systems on behalf of
        the calling client.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Pre-requisits</title>

    <para>The installation of this module requires the externalised
    authenticator capability of JBoss which was added from JBoss 4.0.5.GA,
    these instructions have been prepared against JBoss 4.2.2.GA.</para>

    <para><link
    linkend="???">http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/ExternalizeTomcatAuthenticators</link></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>